A Guide to the Norfolk & Western Railway and Associated Companies Collection, 1851-1978
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Norfolk & Western Railway and Associated Companies Collection, 1851-1978.
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms.2009.037
3.7 cu. ft. 6 boxes; 1 oversize folder
Collection of records relating to the Norfolk & Western Railway and several of its predecessor and subsidiary lines and other associated enterprises, including the Atlantic & Danville Railway; Bluefield Inn; Deepwater Railway; Hotel Roanoke; New Jersey, Indiana & Illinois Railroad; New York, Chicago and St. Louis Railroad; Norfolk and Petersburg Railroad; Norfolk and Western Railroad; Roanoke Machine Works; Shenandoah Valley Railroad; Tidewater Railway; and the Winston-Salem Southbound Railway. Included are such materials as financial and legal documents, reports, maps, construction files, printed materials, and Norfolk & Western standard plans.
Norfolk and Western Railroad Company.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The first accrual of the Norfolk & Western Railway and Associated Companies Collection was purchased in 2008. The second accrual was purchased from the same source in 2009.
Historical Information
The Norfolk & Western Railway was established through a reorganization of the bankrupt Norfolk and Western Railroad in 1896, the latter company itself having arisen from the Atlantic, Mississippi & Ohio Railroad, a successor to the Norfolk and Petersburg Railroad. Through expansion and various mergers, the N&W grew to become a major U.S. carrier, serving 14 states. The company manufactured steam locomotives at its own Roanoke Machine Works (established in Roanoke, Virginia in 1882), and among the railroad's affiliated holdings were several hotels (represented in this collection by the Bluefield Inn and the Hotel Roanoke). Among the company's larger merger acquisitions was the New York, Chicago and St. Louis Railroad--the "Nickel Plate Road"--in 1964. (Other acquisitions represented in this collection are the Atlantic & Danville Railway (1962); the New Jersey, Indiana & Illinois Railroad (through acquisition of the Wabash Railroad, 1962); and the Winston-Salem Southbound Railway (acquired and operated jointly with the Atlantic Coast Line Railroad, 1909).) In 1982, the N&W combined with the Southern Railway to form Norfolk Southern Corporation.
Scope and Content
This collection contains materials from the Norfolk & Western Railway, several of its predecessor and subsidiary lines, and associated companies. The collection contains such items as financial and legal documents, reports, maps, plans, timetables, work documents, and printed materials.
The operations of the Norfolk & Western Railway are represented in the collection by a diverse array of materials, including such items as seniority rosters, descriptions / classifications of the company's rolling stock, and printed materials (including legal agreements and a list of Roanoke sidings and team tracks). The N&W materials also include several timetables, train orders, and memoranda from the Passenger Traffic Department. Most significantly, perhaps, the materials include a bound set of standard plans issued by the office of the company's chief engineer. The standards book includes specifications for company-manufactured or -constructed buildings, tools, signs, roadways, bridges, tunnels, appurtenances, etc. Among the remaining materials are a number of financial documents, including such materials as account statements and disbursement vouchers. Also relating to various aspects of daily company operations are several items, including a record book of clerical personnel at the Bluefield Yards; a conductor's train book, bulletins from Crew, Virginia; Passenger Traffic Department circular letters; and time return and delay reports.
The collection also includes several construction job files for the New York, Chicago and St. Louis Railroad Company (the "Nickel Plate Road") projects in Ohio during the late 1950s. Included in the files for jobs at Huron, Canton, Toledo, Massilon, Georgetown, Fremont, Ironville, Cleveland, and Burbank, are maps, legal documents, balance sheets, correspondence, and reports.
Among the materials in the collection representing other companies are antebellum payment records from the Norfolk and Petersburg Railroad (including payrolls and disbursement vouchers). From the Norfolk and Western Railroad are various financial and legal documents, including account statements, purchase vouchers, and reports, all largely relating to the company's reorganization. Among the many other companies represented in the collection are: the Deepwater Railway; Hotel Roanoke; New Jersey, Indiana & Illinois Railroad; Roanoke Machine Works; Shenandoah Valley Railroad; Tidewater Railway; and Winston-Salem Southbound Railway.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by company name, then alphabetically by topic or document type.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections holds several other manuscript collections as well as books relating to the Norfolk & Western and its affiliates. Consult the Guide to Manuscript Sources for Railroad History Research and the library's catalog.
Separated Material
The Norfolk & Western Railway and Associated Companies Collection was purchased in two accruals. With the first accrual, materials that were determined to relate specifically to the Norfolk & Western, its predecessors and affiliates were retained in this collection (Ms2009-037). The personal and working papers of Chapman J. French, a civil engineer employed by the company, were easily distinguishable and were separated to the newly created Chapman J. French Papers (Ms2009-034). Materials that did not relate in any way to the N&W were separated into the following individual collections:
Mine Hill & Schuylkill Haven Railroad Stock Certificates (Ms2009-035)
New River Mineral Company Stock Certificate (Ms2009-036)
Philadelphia & Reading Railroad Receipts (Ms2009-038)
Raleigh Coal & Coke Company Rail Spur Drawing (Ms2009-039)
Reed Island Iron Company Receipts (Ms2009-040)
Rock Island Lines Insurance Booklet (Ms2009-041)
Sullivan Railroad Company Stock Certificate (Ms2009-042)
Tennessee, Alabama & Georgia Railroad Annual Report (Ms2009-043)
Tennessee, Alabama & Georgia Railway Annual Report (Ms2009-044)
Thomas Wood and Company Freight Records (Ms2009-045)
Virginia Iron, Coal and Coke Company Receipts (Ms2009-046)
Much of the second accrual was likewise divided between the Norfolk & Western Railway and Associated Companies Collection and the Chapman J. French Papers. In the second accrual, however, materials that did not relate to the N&W were separated into a newly created collection bearing the name of the collector, Wayne Perkins.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
New York, Chicago, and St. Louis Railway Company.; Norfolk and Western Railroad Company.
Local Subjects:
Local/Regional History; Railroad
Contents List
- A-C (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Atlantic & Danville Railway right-of-way and track map,1927., [see Oversize Materials]
  - Atlantic, Mississippi and Ohio Railroad receipts,1876-1881., [2 items]
  - Bluefield Inn receipts,1893-1897.
- Deepwater Railway financial records, 1903-1906, n.d., [3 folders] (Box-folder 1-2)
- E-G (Box-folder 1-3)
  - East River Railroad - West Virginia legislation,1882.
  - Erie-Lackawanna Railway train orders,1976.
- Hotel Roanoke
  - Receipts, 1893-1898, n.d. (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Extra labor payroll records, 1940-1941. (Box-folder 1-5)
- Howard Collieries grocery invoices, 1928. (Box-folder 1-6)
- I-M (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Lynchburg and Durham Railroad - Virginia legislation,1892.
- New Jersey, Indiana and Illinois Railroad, 1904-1905. (Box-folder 1-8)
- New River Plateau Railroad - Virginia incorporation act, 1888. (Box-folder 1-9)
- New York, Chicago and St. Louis Railroad ("Nickel Plate Road") job files
  - Dredging of dock facilities at Huron, Ohio (Job J-4239), 1959-1962. (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Grade separation on U.S. Route 62 at Canton, Ohio (Job J-4123), 1957-1958. (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Grade separation structure over expressway at Toledo, Ohio (Job J-4122), 1955-1958., [2 folders] [see also Oversize Materials] (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Installation of operation recorders at Massilon, Ohio (Job J-4142), 1956-1957. (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Installation of partition at Georgetown, Ohio (Job J-4165), 1958. (Box-folder 1-14)
  - Relocation of U.S. Route 20 at Fremont, Ohio (Job J-4125), 1957-1959. (Box-folder 1-15)
  - Removal of clay deposit and replacement of pole line at East Canton, Ohio (Job J-4162), 1957-1959. (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Replacement of car wash building at Ironville, Ohio (Job J-4166), 1957-1961. (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Replacement of plank walks with slag screenings at Ironville, Ohio (Job J-4170), 1957-1961. (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Restoration of Cuyahoga Valley Railroad turnout at Cleveland, Ohio (Job J-4164), 1956. (Box-folder 1-19)
  - Separation of track grades for State Route 1 at Burbank, Ohio (Job J-4194), 1958-1960. (Box-folder 2-1)
- Norfolk and Petersburg Railroad payroll and vouchers, 1855-1859. (Box-folder 2-2-3)
- Norfolk and Western Railroad
  - Account statements and receipts, 1883-1887, n.d. (Box-folder 2-4-6)
  - Bonds, securities and mortgages, 1881-1905, n.d. (Box-folder 2-7-8)
  - Claims, 1882-1886. (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Claims, 1887., [2 folders] (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Correspondence and memoranda, 1883-1905. (Box-folder 2-11)
  - Employee pay and travel expense records, 1882-1887. (Box-folder 2-12)
  - Freight bills, 1883-1887. (Box-folder 2-13)
  - Legal documents, 1884-1896. (Box-folder 2-14)
  - Map of depot grounds and proposed arrangement for coal tracks at Central Station, n.d., [see Oversize Materials]
  - Purchase vouchers, 1882-1887. (Box-folder 2-15-16)
  - Reports and statements, 1882-1897. (Box-folder 3-1-2)
- Norfolk & Western Railway
  - Account statements, 1908-1916. (Box-folder 3-3)
  - Buffalo Creek (West Virginia) deeds, 1903-1917. (Box-folder 3-4)
  - Burns legal files
    - Mollie and J. Taze Howard (guaridans of Burns and Lois Aston) v. N&W, 1897-1900, n.d. (Box-folder 3-5)
    - Miriam E. Jackson v. N&W, 1894. (Box-folder 3-6)
    - S. N. Johnson v. N&W, 1893-1905, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 3-7)
    - B. H. Jones v. N&W, 1896. (Box-folder 3-8)
    - Lebanon Hardware Company v. N&W, 1905-1907. (Box-folder 3-9)
    - Ida Sexton (by Lafayette Sexton) v. N&W, 1895-1896. (Box-folder 3-10)
    - B. J. Wysor v. N&W, 1905. (Box-folder 3-11)
    - L. Finney v. E. E. Price (N&W, garnishee), 1904. (Box-folder 3-12)
  - Civilian Conservation Corps - Camp McArthur (Damascus, Virginia) train orders, 1933-1935. (Box-folder 3-13)
  - Clerical personnel record book [Bluefield Yards], 1931-1939. (Box-folder 3-14)
  - Company fact book, [1949?]. (Box-folder 4-1)
  - Conductor's train book (W. F. Oliver, conductor), 1954. (Box-folder 4-2)
  - Crewe, Virginia superintendent's office bulletins, 1955. (Box-folder 4-3)
  - Disbursement vouchers, 1908-1918. (Box-folder 4-4-6)
  - Employee travel expense statements, 1908-1918. (Box-folder 4-7)
  - Freight bills, 1900-1909. (Box-folder 4-8)
  - Inventory of materials and supplies on hand, 1917. (Box-folder 4-9)
  - Materials and supplies disbursed statements, 1918. (Box-folder 4-10)
  - Passenger Traffic Department circular letters, 1945-1957. (Box-folder 4-11)
  - Rolling stock description and classification (Box-folder 4-12)
    - Locomotives, 1941.
    - Locomotives, 1953.
    - Passenger equipt. cars, 1945.
  - Seniority rosters (Box-folder 4-13)
    - Conductors - Pocahontas Division, 1957.
    - Telegraphers and agents - Radford Division, 1930.
    - Telegraphers - Radford Division, 1947.
    - Telegraphers - Radford Division, 1958.
    - Telegraphers - Radford Division, 1960.
  - Standard plans book, 1901-1967. (Box-folder 4-14)
  - Statements and reports, 1895-1972, n.d. (Box-folder 5-1)
  - Time return and delay reports (James P. Catron, conductor), 1949-1955. (Box-folder 5-2)
  - Timetables A-Q (Box-folder 5-3)
    - Lake Erie Division no. 200, 1965.
    - Muncie Division no. 200, 1965., [2 copies]
    - Norfolk Division no. 16, 1959.
  - Timetables R (Box-folder 5-4)
    - Radford Division no. 1, 1930.
    - Radford Division no. 2, 1931.
    - Radford Division no. 7, 1947.
    - Radford Division no. 34, 1930.
    - Radford Division no. 37, 1930.
    - Radford Division no. 38, 1930.
  - Timetables S-Z (Box-folder 5-5)
    - Shenandoah Division no. 9, 1955.
    - Shenandoah Division no. 6, 1975.
  - Track charts - Eastern Region, Norfolk Division, 1978. (Box-folder 5-6)
  - Train orders, 1954-1976. (Box-folder 5-7-9)
  - Treasurer's office company reorganization papers, 1896. (Box-folder 5-10)
  - Treasurer's office company reorganization papers, 1897-1902. (Box-folder 5-11)
  - Printed material (Box-folder 5-12)
    - "Agreement Between the Director General of Railroads and Norfolk and Western Railway Company and Other Corporations," 1918.
    - "Alphabetical-numerical List of Sidings and Team Tracks Within Roanoke Terminal Switching Limits," 1956.
    - "Final Settlement Between the Director General of Railroads and the Norfolk and Western Railway Company and Other Corporations," 1923.
    - "Hints on Health and First Aid," 1917.
    - "Indenture of Lease Between Pocahontas Coal and Coke Company, Lessor, and Illinois Steel Company, Lessee, and Norfolk and Western Railway Company...," 1901.
    - "Instructions Covering Collection of Federal Tax on Transportation of Persons, Seating or Sleeping Accommodations, etc., and Transportation of Property," 1950.
    - "Instructions to Agents, Conductors, Yard Masters and Others, Governing the Use of Automatic, Self-locking, Consecutively-numbered Car Seals," 1908.
    - "Notice of Annual Meeting of Stockholders," 1978.
    - "Regulations and Requirements Governing Physical Examinations of Applicants for Employment," 1928.
    - "Transportation Charges and Regulations for Occupancy of Space in Sleeping Cars and Parlor Cars...," 1949-1950., [2 items]
  - Miscellanea (Box-folder 5-13)
    - Pay rates, 1952.
    - Pocahontas Division superintendent bulletin notice (no. 4430) regarding vacations, 1949.
    - Applications for increase in work force or rate of pay, 1919-1937.
    - Conductor's check of train register, n.d.
    - Inspection certificate of empty box car, 1970.
- O-Q (Box-folder 6-1)
  - Pittsburgh & West Virginia Railway freight claim payment to Union Pacific Railroad,1960.
- Roanoke Machine Works
  - Statements of account with Norfolk & Western Railway, 1887. (Box-folder 6-2)
  - Assorted records. (Box-folder 6-3)
    - Disbursement vouchers, 1884.
    - Materials and supplies account, 1889.
    - Contract with Girard Life Insurance, Annuity & Trust, 1889.
    - Contract with Fidelity Insurance, Trust and Safe Deposit Company, 1887.
- Roanoke and Southern Railway legislative charter (North Carolina), 1893. (Box-folder 6-4)
- Shenandoah Valley Railroad
  - Correspondence/memoranda and disbursement vouchers, 1883-1897. (Box-folder 6-5)
  - Legal documents, 1887-1890, n.d. (Box-folder 6-6)
- South and Western Railroad letter from general counsel J. Norment Powell regarding McEwen v. Dawson Coal & Coke, 1907. (Box-folder 6-7)
- Tidewater Railway
  - Journal vouchers, 1906-1910, n.d. (Box-folder 6-8-10)
  - Journal entries and other financial records, 1905-1909. (Box-folder 6-11)
- U-V (Box-folder 6-12)
  - Virginia and Tennessee railroad receipts, 1851-1859.
  - Virginia Company legal and financial documents,1888-1942, n.d.
  - Virginia Mineral Railway legislative act of incorporation,1880.
  - Virginian Railway financial records,1909-1931.
- W-Z (Box-folder 6-13)
  - Washington and Western Railroad legislative act of incorporation (Virginia), 1889.
  - Winston-Salem Southbound Railway annual report,1914.
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS (Folder Oversize 1)
  - Atlantic & Danville Railway Company right-of-way and track map, 1927.
  - New York, Chicago and St. Louis Railroad Company ("Nickel Plate Road") grade separation structure over expressway at Toledo, Ohio (Job J-4122), 1955.
  - Norfolk and Western Railroad map of depot grounds and proposed arrangement for coal tracks at Central Station, n.d.
  - "Official Map of Percentage Groups in Central Freight Association Territory... for West-bound Freight Rates," n.d.
  - Norfolk & Western Railway Scioto Division - Sandusky district right-of-way and track map,1970.
  - Norfolk & Western Railway Company map showing lands on Buffalo Creek (Mingo County, West Virginia),1918.